Moving on to congestive heart failure,
this is when the heart fails to pump appropriately.
It's divided into right and left-sided failure.
Some causes of left-sided failure include ischemia.
If you decrease the blood flow to the heart,
that would damage the myocardium,
and hence the myocardium would not function properly.
A hypertension can do it.
The idea is that when you have hypertension,
you get concentric left ventricular hypertrophy.
As there's an increased stress on the heart,
the heart is going to undergo hypertrophy
in order to be able to deal with that stress.
Now, the more that you get hypertrophy of the wall of the heart,
the harder it is to be able to oxygenate that wall,
because, of course, if this is the normal thickness of the wall,
and now you make the wall this thick,
you've got to be able to oxygenate all of this extra mass of muscle.
And so the consequence of long-standing hypertension with hypertrophy
is that eventually you start getting ischemic damage to the heart,
which then eventually can result in a left-sided heart failure.
Dilated cardiomyopathy is a disorder
in which you get four-chamber dilatation of the heart,
left and right atrium and left and right ventricle.
And as you get dilatation, you're going to stretch the muscle,
and as you stretch the muscle,
it's not going to be able to contract as well.
And so that would be another cause of left-sided failure.
Myocardial infarction, of course, if you infarct the myocardium,
it's not going to be functioning.
And so that can result in a left-sided failure.
And finally, restrictive cardiomyopathy is a disorder
where you can't fill the heart appropriately.
And of course, if you can't fill the heart,
you're not going to be able to pump blood appropriately.
And so you'll get a left-sided failure.
So these are some of the important causes of left-sided failure.
The clinical consequences of left-sided heart failure
will be predominantly based on pulmonary congestion.
When the heart can't pump the blood forward,
it's going to pile up backward,
and it's going to start piling up within the blood vessels of the lung,
i.e. pulmonary congestion.
Now this will increase the hydrostatic pressure within the blood vessels,
leading to pulmonary edema with dyspnea.
In addition, they'll have paroxysmal nocturnal dyspnea,
which is where they get dyspnea as they lay flat over a period of hours.
They'll have orthopnea, where they get dyspnea
if they lay flat over a period of just a few minutes.
In addition, they'll have crackles,
which represents the edema or the fluid
within the interstitial space of the lung.
Another consequence of pulmonary congestion
will be that there will be rupture of some of the capillaries
that are engorged.
Now when these capillaries rupture,
blood will then leak from the capillaries into the alveolar air sacs,
and the macrophages of the alveolar air sacs will consume that blood.
As they consume that blood,
they're going to be consuming a ton of iron,
and so iron will begin to pile up within those macrophages,
and those are called hemocytorin-laden macrophages,
and also known as heart failure cells.
Here's a picture of the hemocytorin-laden macrophages.
This is the alveolar air sac,
and you can see that you've got these macrophages
within the alveolar air sac that are loaded with hemocytorin.
Again, hemocytorin-laden macrophages are also known as heart failure cells.
An additional consequence of left-sided heart failure
will be that there will be decreased forward perfusion.
Perhaps the greatest consequence of this decreased forward perfusion
will be that you'll get activation of the renin-angiotensin system.
Recall that if there is decreased blood flow to the kidneys,
the juxtaglomerular apparatus will get activated, releasing renin.
Renin will then convert angiotensinogen to angiotensin I.
Angiotensin I will get converted to angiotensin II
by angiotensin-converting enzyme.
Now, angiotensin II will then do two things.
Number one, it'll constrict the arterioles,
increasing the total peripheral resistance.
And number two, it'll go to the adrenal gland,
causing release of aldosterone, which will come back to the kidney,
cause resorption of sodium,
and eventually water will follow so that you increase the blood volume.
Now, imagine if a patient has congestive heart failure
and you increase the total peripheral resistance,
you're just going to exacerbate the failure.
In addition, if the patient has congestive heart failure
and you increase the blood volume,
that's only further going to, again, exacerbate the problem.
And so this results in a downward spiral of the congestive heart failure.
And that's why one of the mainstays of treatment of congestive heart failure
is an ACE inhibitor, and that's particularly high yield.
Now, moving on to the right side,
right-sided heart failure is most commonly due to left failure.
Illustrating this is this is the left heart
and it's draining the pulmonary circuit.
Then it's important to know that the right heart
is actually feeding the pulmonary circuit.
And so, if there is backup of blood into the pulmonary circuit,
eventually that would back up into the right heart
and then you'd get a right heart failure.
And so, again, very high yield to know
that the most common cause of right-sided heart failure
is actually left-sided failure.
Other important causes of right-sided failure
include left to right shunts.
If you put extra blood into the right side,
for example, with a shunt,
so if this is right atrium, right ventricle,
left atrium, left ventricle,
if there is a shunt from, for example,
the left ventricle to the right ventricle,
that's going to then increase the amount of blood
that goes into the right ventricle,
increasing the risk for right heart failure.
And then finally, chronic lung disease can also result
in a right-sided heart failure.
The idea here is that when you have lung disease,
you develop hypoxia.
And one of the consequences of hypoxia
is that the blood vessels in the lung
will constrict in response to that hypoxia.
Now, imagine if you have hypoxia throughout the lung,
then the blood vessels of the entire lung
are going to constrict,
and the right heart will have to pump
against those constricted blood vessels.
Eventually, the right heart will fail,
and that's called core pulmonale.
Now, the clinical features of right-sided heart failure
are going to be due to congestion
of those things that feed the right heart.
So, of course, the jugular vein feeds into the right heart,
so the patients can get jugular venous distension.
Of course, the venous system coming from the liver
and the spleen also feeds into the right heart,
and so the patients can develop painful hepatosplenomegaly.
One of the consequences of long-standing congestion
in the liver would be cirrhosis,
and when that occurs, we call that cardiac cirrhosis.
Finally, because the lower extremities are also draining
into the right heart,
you'll get increased hydrostatic pressure
within the lower extremities,
resulting in a dependent pitting edema.
Here's a picture of a congested liver.
Recall that when you look at the surface of a normal liver,
the color should be absolutely equal across the liver.
However, note here that we've got all these splotches of red
throughout the liver representing congested central veins.
This then creates this variegated color to the surface of the liver
which resembles a nutmeg,
and so this is also called the nutmeg liver.
And that concludes our section on congestive heart failure.